Wilbur Joseph Cohen Papers 5222
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wilbur Joseph Cohen Papers
1937-1942
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cohen, Wilbur Joseph
5222
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
The collection consists of the papers and pamphlets collected by Mr. Cohen and relating to the Social Security Advisory Council during 1937-1938.
5556497
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 25, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 21, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Wilbur J. Cohen was director of the Research and Statistics Bureau of the Wisconsin Health, Education, and Welfare Department, and technical advisor of the U.S. Advisory Council on Social Security. The Advisory Council was appointed by the Senate Finance Committee in cooperation with the U.S. Social Security Board and was composed of representatives of the public, employers, and employees. The purpose of the Advisory Council was to cooperate with a special subcommittee of the Committee on Finance (Senators Pat Harrison, Harry Flood Byrd, Arthur J. Vandenberg) and the Social Security Board in the study of problems relative to social security, with special attention to the problem of financing an old age insurance system.
Scope and Contents
Includes letters, memoranda, and reports of the meetings of the United States Social Security Advisory Council during the period Cohen served as its technical advisor (1937-1938), as well as correspondence, reports, notes, pamphlets, ,statistical studies and other documents assembled by Cohen, relating to economic security.
Correspondence (1932-1948) discusses old age benefits in general, including methods of financing,, the wage base, women's eligibility, and various alternative schemes. Disability insurance is also examined: its feasibiity, benefit specifications, and the medical, surgical, and institutional care of annuitants. Revisions to Title II of the Social Security Act are discussed, including the possibility of extending coverage to employees of charitable agencies and state governments. Changes in AC 12, especially coverage of women and the children of deceased wage earners, are mentione,d as are proposas for the coverage of dependent children, agricultural laborers, the self-employed and widows under AC 13. Coverage of dependent children, still an issue in AC 14, is discussed, as is the exclusion of mental illness from th edisability definition. Title VIII of the Act, especially in relation to the inclusion of state and charitable workers, is the subject of correspondence, as is the possibility of a guaranteed annual wage.
The major correspondents include Wilbur J. Cohen, J. Douglas Brown (chairman, Advisory Council on Social Security), Arthur J. Altmeyer (chairman, Social Security Board), Eleanor Lansing Dulles (chief, Division of Old Age Benefits Research, Bureau of Research and Statistics), John J. Corson (director, Bureau of Old Age Insurance), Murray W. Latimer (chairman, Railroad Retirment Board), Alanson W. Wilcox (assistant general counsel), Edwin F. Witte (professor, University of Wisconsin, Department of Economics), I.S. Falk (acting director, Bureau of Research and Statistics),, and W.R. Williamson (actuarial consultant).
Reports and papers (ca. 1935-1957) on the overall issue of economic security (old age security, unemployment compensation, aid to children and the handicapped) include a report by I.S. Falk on permanent and total disability (1938); an analysis by Abraham Epstein of the federal old age insurance plan; a statement by Emile Rieve (president, Textile Workers of America) suporting a national system of unemployment insurance; documents regarding state vs. federal control of unemployment insurance; a report by Eleanor Dulles to the Advisory Council on her examination of the social security reserve problem (1957); a study of old age assistance and unemployment insurance in foreign countries; documents concerning state economic security plans in the 1930s; and documents regarding the implementation of social security and actuarial and statistical analyses of the program by various subdivisions of the Social Security Board, private and state agencies.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Social security.; Pensions; Pensions -- Finance; Unemployment insurance.; Unemployment insurance -- Governement policy; Pensions -- Agriculture -- United States; Self-employed -- Pensions -- United States; Mothers' pensions -- United States; Women -- Pensions -- United States; Altmeyer, Arthur J. (Arthur Joseph), 1891-1972.; Brown, J. Douglas (James Douglas), 1898-1986; Cohen, Wilbur Joseph, 1913-; Corson, John Jay, 1905-; Dulles, Eleanor Lansing, 1895-1996; Epstein, Abraham, 1892-1942; Falk, I. S. (Isidore Sydney), 1899-1984; Latimer, Murray W.; Rieve, Emil, 1892-1975; Williamson, W. R. (William Rulon), 1889-; Witte, Edwin E. (Edwin Emil), 1887- 1960; International Conference of Employment Security Agencies; United States. Advisory Council on Social Security (1937-1938). Interim Committee; United States. Social Security Board
5556497
- 025 - Advisory Council J. Douglas Brown Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 025 - Advisory Council November 5 & 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 025 - Advisory Council November 5 & 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 025 - Advisory Council Statements December 10 and 11, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 025 - Advisory Council Statements February 18-19, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 025 - Advisory Council Feb. 18-19, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 025 - Advisory Council April 29-30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 025 - Advisory Council Statements April 29-30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 025 - Advisory Council December 10 and 11, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 025 - Miscellaneous AC Plans and Materials, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 025 - Principles Concerning Revision of Benefits, Etc., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 025 - AC 13, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 011.1 - Amendments AC - 14, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Preliminary Outline of Plan AC-14, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 011.1 - Amendments AC-14, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 011.1 Amendments AC-14, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Principles, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Methods of Financing, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Cohen's Letters to Gray Report on Integration of S.S. & Teacher Retirement, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bill to Amend the Social Security Act and Related Materials 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Benefit Payment Procedure July 1937- July 1939, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Federal Security Agency Folder 1, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Federal Security Agency Folder 2, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Legislative Information on Bills Affecting Unemployment Compensation, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- State Operations Bulletin No. 2, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Summary of Recommendations of the Advisory Council on OASI, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Advisory Council on Social Security, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Confidential, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Confidential, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Confidential, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Confidential, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Advisory Council Materials December 4-5, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Social Security Board, 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- National Health Conference, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- President's Interdepartmental Committee to Coordinate Health and Welfare Activities (National Health Conference), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- National Health Conference, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- National Health Conference, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- National Health Conference, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Interdepartmental Committee to Coordinate Health and Welfare Activities, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Mr. Altmeyer, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- California Disability Insurance Program, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- New Jersey Disability Insurance Program, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Railroad Temporary Disability Insurance Program, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Temporary Disability Insurance, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Temporary Disability Insurance Coordinated with Unemployment Insurance, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Temporary Disability Insurance Coordinated with Unemployment Insurance, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- An Economic Security Program for the United States Vol. 1, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- An Economic Security Program for the United States, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Employment Service Handbook of Information, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- 1939 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Old-Age Benefits, 1932-1936 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Proposals for Coordinating Guaranteed Annual Wages & Unemployment Insurance, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- A Dynamic Analysis of Unemployment Statistics, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 23)